All right, everyone, in this video, we're going to talk about a significant concept, which is
usually taken for granted. It's thought to be understood, but often the principles
that lie beneath are made to look like complex or at the best case, they're not understood properly.
And we're going to talk about before we move on, we're going to talk about object oriented
programming. That is in short, what we call as O P or the language that is an object oriented
programming that follows the O principle. We call it the object oriented programming language,
and Java is just one of them. The others being, there is PHP, there is C sharp, there is Python,
a lot of object oriented programming languages out there. But we're just going to obviously talk
about with the perspective of how we do things in Java. But to start with, we're just going to
look into the details of object oriented programming. And this idea has gained a lot of traction
over the last few years, hugely popular idea, hugely popular way to program and to code things.
So let's just have a look at what this means. So first things first, what is object oriented
programming? So it can have many definitions or no concrete definition at all, depending on whom you
ask. So I'll keep you keep things simple for you again. And we'll just talk about object oriented
programming with respect to the four principles of it, the four pillars or the four features of
object oriented programming, what we like to call it. Right. And once you understand what those four
principles are, then you indirectly have understood what object oriented programming is all about.
And we take real world analogies, because an object oriented programming, what we do in coding
that is immediately or that is quickly relatable to how we do things in the real world. That's why
I'll take real world analogies for you to have a great understanding of these principles. And
these four principles that we're going to talk about starting with that is abstraction.
That is the first principle we're talking about when when we discuss object oriented programming.
And again, as I said, to make you understand what object oriented programming is, I'll just take a
real world example of all these principles. So abstraction, you can think about abstraction as being
hiding complexity and showing only what is necessary to interact with the object that you are
dealing with. In other words, it just focuses on what an object does, not how it does it. Right.
So we focus again to reiterate on what an object does, but not how it actually does it. Right.
And now there can be many analogies that come to your mind. This is just one of those analogies.
Think about a television remote, right. And what comes to your mind when you think about a TV
remote, you see buttons on like change the channels, change the volume up and down. There is
change the input source. There is there are number number pad on a remote. There is the power button.
So while dealing with this remote, you don't really need to understand infrared signals or even
pixel frequencies or circuit roads, obviously, which is within that tiny box out there. And
for watching a show, you just need to deal with those buttons. And that's why this remote provides
a simpler interface for a complex machine, which lies beneath it. Right. And that is a great analogy
of understanding abstraction, where we just talk about it again, as I said, you just don't need
to go into details, not do not need to know and understand the complexities. You just need to know
what something does. And in our in program programmatic words, what an object does not actually
how it does this. And in the code in Java, we'll do that with interfaces and abstract classes,
abstract classes. Right. And when we come across those particular topics, we'll just see how Java
implements abstraction in a really beautiful way. Right. And the second principle,
I'm going to talk about is abstraction, sorry, encapsulation, abstraction we already had a look at.
Right. Now, you talked about abstraction. And I gave you the analogy of an object of a remote.
We need to be focused on how and or what an object does, but not on how it does is does it.
But encapsulation, you can think about binding or bundling data and methods that use it
into a single unit like a class. And that is hiding the internal state, hiding the complexities
again from the end user. Now, you might wonder if structure and cap station, they look similar
and very do, but there are there is a difference in perspective, in perception, and so hugely
significant, significant difference. Right. Now, think about again, another analogy that comes to
your mind is if you talk about, but again, as I said, there can be many such examples out there.
Let's say one of the examples that I always take in my classes is let's say we have a person,
a good friend, John, and John has entertainment magazine at his home. Right. And he keeps it in the
lobby on the table. Why? He wants it to be readable by his family members, cousins, acquaintances,
and friends. Right. But John, the same person has another position, another commodity with him.
He has a video, a video game that he wants to be accessible by himself and his brothers and sisters.
So only those folks have keys to that room where John keeps the video game. The third commodity
that my friend John has is some golden cash with John at all times, just wants to be for himself.
So he gets the locker, right, puts the golden cash into that locker, and there's just one key
which is around the neck at all times with John, right. No one else has access to it. So what
does this tell you? This tells you that John, the same person has different things with him,
different items, but he's able to define their excess. And that in short, my friends is what we
call as encapsulation defining the excess defining the scope. And in programming in Java, you will
see I would do that with the help of private instance variables and public get a set of methods.
I'm more on that later on when we actually write the code, but that is how we would implement
encapsulation in in Java. And again, the key difference is now with abstraction and encapsulation
is you would think that encapsulation is about security and protecting the internal state
from the outside interference. And on the other, an abstraction is hiding the complexity. It's
about keeping things simple and providing a cleaner interface to the end user like that TV remote,
right. And then on the implementation level, you say encapsulation happens at the code level,
that is private instance variables, as I told you, but abstraction on the other hand, it happens at
the design level, right. So again, go back and think about that TV remote example, right. And
just in other words, you will say encapsulation says, you cannot touch this on the other hand,
abstraction says, you don't need to know this, right. Again, for iteration and encapsulation,
you can't touch this, but abstraction, you don't need to know this, right. That's the primary
differences between encapsulation and abstraction, right. The third idea of object when
into programming, we're going to talk about is polymorfism, right. And just to understand,
polymorfism again, we'll take a real world example. Again, there can be multiple examples
out there, right. So one of those examples is, let's say we have another friend and my friend's
name, this time is, isronic, right. So what happens now is, Ronick on a normal day on a fine day,
he looks like this, right. Just in a normal mood, right. That is day one, right. But normal on
another day, he comes to the college, right. And his friends see him something like this,
this thing, Ronick, that is, right, a bit sad. And that is day two. And they ask him, what is wrong?
It says that I'm feeling a bit sad about I lost a game of free kid that I played yesterday,
I'd still make me sad. On the third day, Ronick, the same person comes in and he is looking
like this. That is crying, unfortunately. And friends upon an acquiring come to know that
Ronick was, was not given the pocket money by his father, and he cannot get things in the
cafeteria today. And Ronick on the fourth day, he comes in and he's seen like this. That is happy,
like we always want to see him. And upon inquiring, the friends come to know that Ronick
has been gifted a smartwatch today by his parents upon securing good grades in the last exam.
So now what does this tell you? You see, Ronick is the same person, but has different forms
on different things, right. Same person, right. So in short, we call it one face, many forms,
and that my friends is for the more present. And we do it a couple of ways in Java or in object
20 programming languages. I brief you through that when we come up on that particular section, but for
now one face, many forms, and this is just one of the ideas. Just think about after this video is
done about the different analogies that you can bring to the table that are different than mine,
but still make us understand these particular, particular features or principles of object 20
programming. I'll be looking forward to your comments. The fourth idea, we talk about the principles
that is, and that is inheritance. And in now, because of the fourth idea, and it's very easily
understood, you can take many, many examples out there, but let's just take a classic example that
I often take. And it's like, for example, now I have one more friend and the name of which is
let me think randomly, and that is, let's just think about it, that is Santa, right? Now, what
happens is, Santa generally hears about herself from her friends from her relatives, that is your
height is exactly as your mother's. You speak in the same tune as your father's, right? And you
have a way of walking that resembles your grandmother. So what is that? That is, she is inheriting
some properties through her lineage from her parents and grandparents. This my friends has called
re usability of Corinne short, that is inheritance, I define it as reusable. You could write
Corinne and then reuse it in many forms. That is one of the great features or principles of
object 20 programming. And that is inheritance. And now when you have defined these four principles,
you've indirectly defined what object oriented programming is about. It's just about these
four principles. That is no one has ever seen or felt object oriented programming like, oh,
what that is? Oh, be standing there or sitting or lying there? No, it's just a tangible idea,
right? It's intangible. It's right. Then you don't mind, right? That's why I see
object when you're programming is not something solid or tangible. It is a way of programming.
It's an approach towards programming. It is a paradigm, right? You did the same things as
see as you would do in Java, but the way the approach would change because here we're falling
object oriented programming, right? And Java, the language, it beautifully implements all of these
four principles and we'll have a look at them time after time in this course. But I'll be looking
forward, as I said, to your own analogies, but you can think about what comes to your mind in the
coming section.